Guide to the Residential Life Reference Collection, 1922-2001
Duke University. University Archives
Residential Life Reference Collection 1922-2001
Duke University. University Archives
1.3 linear feet Extent: 1000 Items
The Residential Life Reference Collection contains files of reports, clippings, handbooks, and other materials concerning residential life at the University. This collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research.
UA.01.11.0050
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Residential Life Reference Collection was compiled by University Archives staff from a variety of sources.
Historical Note
After the opening of Duke's West Campus in 1930, the arrangement and administration of residential life at the University remained fairly static through the 1950s. Some fraternities had the same blocks of rooms for decades. Then, beginning with the work of the University Committee on Long-Range Planning (1958-1962), residential arrangements and administration came under close review. That process has continued. Groups involved in it have included the Undergraduate Faculty Council, its successor, the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS), and its successor, the Arts and Sciences Council, the West Campus Community Council (WCCC), the Community Council of the Woman's College (CoCoWoCo), the Residential Life Committee, the Residential Policy Committee, and successor groups.
Collection Overview
Reports, subject files, housing proposals, policy statements, regulations, newspaper clippings, flyers, brochures, announcements, handbooks and guides for resident advisors, dormitory floor plans, correspondence, memoranda and chronologies of changes in residential life, 1920s-1990s. Major subjects include residential planning and programming, on- and off-campus housing, housing for graduate and professional students and married students, the administration of residential life, federations and other housing arrangements, the work of resident advisors and faculty-in-residence, experimental living-learning arrangements, and non-Greek houses and associations. Groups represented include Association of Independent Houses, the Council of Federation Presidents, the West Campus Community Council, and various committees.
Subject Headings
Duke University. Association of Independent Houses; Duke University -- Housing; Duke University. Residence Life and Housing Services
Related Material
Office of Residential Life records, 1946-2000
University Archives, Duke University.
Living Groups Reference Collection, 1964-2001.
University Archives, Duke University.
Residential College Task Force records,1985-1987.
University Archives, Duke University.
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, 1922-2001, (2 boxes)
  - Residential life timelines, 1922-1990 (Box 1)
  - Chronology: “Outline of major changes … [in] residential life…, 1967-1993” / Ella Shore
  - Memorandum on Housing Accommodations for Single Graduate and Professional Students, [1961]
  - Housemaster system, 1963 + no date
  - Humanities Corridor, 1965-1966
  - Faculty apartments as a co-educational living-learning dormitory / Carol Dabbs & Lawrence Muhlbaier, 1969
  - A proposal for three experimental federations / Residential Life Committee, 1970
  - A proposal for experimental co-ed dorms / Residential Life Committee, 1971
  - Preliminary report of the Wannamaker Guild, spring 1971
  - Report of the WCCC Committee on Housing Governance, [1971]
  - Campus Community Council, 1971-1972 + no date
  - Undergraduate Residential Philosophy and Policy / Residential Life committee, 1971, 1974
  - Residential Life Committee, 1974-1979
  - Wilson House: the first decade / Amy E. Rouse, 1980
  - Bassett-Brown [Residential] College, 1986-1987
  - Committee for the Study of Student Residential Life, Preliminary findings, April 1969
  - Committee for the Study of Student Residential Life, Report, July 1969
  - Committee for the Study of Student Residential Life, Report, July 1969: reprints
  - Residential Education: An Analysis of Duke University’s Undergraduate Housing Facilities / James DeChaine, July 1971 [proposal]
  - Study of Duke University Residential Life: A Tentative Report / Brian McNally, Educational Testing Service, December 1972
  - An Analysis of the Undergraduate Housing Facilities of Duke University / James A. DeChaine, 1972
  - Duke University Residential Life: An Interim Report / Brian J. McNally & Susan Kerner-Hoeg, Educational Testing Service, January 1973
  - Duke University Residential Life: A Two-Year Comparison / Brian J. McNally, July 1974
  - Federations: Evaluation of the three year trial at Duke University by the Residential Committee of the UFCAS, September 1974
  - Evaluation of the three year trial of federations and co-ed residences at Duke University, December 1974 / Residential Committee of the UFCAS
  - Final Report of the Residential Life Task Force, April 1980
  - Final Report of the Task Force on Federations, February 1982
  - Final Report of the Task Force on Freshman Clusters, April 1982
  - Plan for the Enhancement of Residential and Co-curricular Life, 1994
  - Duke University Residential Programming / Kieran, Timberlake & Harris, 1999
  - Council of Federation Presidents Records, 1981-1982
  - Duke’s College Try: The Attempt to Found a Residential College at Duke University, 1986-1987 / Donald J. Fluke, 1987
  - Faculty Associates Program Annual Report, 1995-1996
  - Association of Independent Houses, “There’s no place like home”, 1975-1981 (Box 2)
  - Housing management brochures, 1975-1990
  - Dormitories, living groups, apartments, undated
  - Memoranda concerning housing, 1920-
  - Off-campus housing, 1969-
  - Orientation, 1989-1992
  - Regulations, [1930s]-1982
  - Room rents, 1962-
  - Office of Residential Life, Residential programming, 1982-1983
  - Office of Residential Life, Residential programming, 1983-1984
  - Bulletin of Men’s Residential Staff, Duke University, 1972-1973
  - Bulletin of the Duke University Residential Staff, 1978-79
  - A Manual for the Duke University Residential Staff, 1978/79, 1981/82, 1984/85, 1987/88, 1990/91 (4 folders)
  - Reference Manual of Programming, 1994/95
  - Upperclass Residential Planning Group, 1997
  - Clippings
    - Married student housing, Erwin Road, 1961-1968
    - Housing crisis, 1975-1984
    - Federations, 1978-1982
    - Residential Life Implementation Committee, 1981
    - Residential Policy Committee, 1980
    - Race and Society Program, 1982-1983
    - Residential life, 1975-2001
    - Residential life, undated